Albert E. Moss Collection 1990.0031
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Alfred E. Moss Collection
undated, 1761-1978
1910-1965, Bulk
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1990.0031
10 Linear Feet
Mr. Albert E. Moss was a faculty member at Connecticut Agricultural College (now the University of Connecticut) for twenty-nine years. He is best known for his work in the field of Forestry. Focus of the collection is survey work on the transfer of land to and from the University of Connecticut.
Biography
Albert E. Moss began his career at Connecticut Agricultural College as an instructor of Forestry in 1914. He became an assistant Professor of Forestry between 1914 and 1927. He eventually rose to the position of full professor of Forestry in 1928 and would hold that position until his retirement in 1943. He is known for his extensive field work on virgin forest tree identification and plantings, documenting logging practices and the rising number of sawmills in the United States, stream and dam improvements, and the restocking of rivers with native fish. He worked in conjunction with the Department of Forestry and Wildlife Management to document government timber sales. Although his main focus was on New England forests, primarily Connecticut lands, his fieldwork took him as far as California. He is known at the University of Connecticut for his surveys and mapping of University land.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the professional work of Albert E. Moss. Included are his extensive field notes, films, and slides pertaining to his work in the field of forestry. The collection also includes the surveys and deeds of lands surrounding the University of Connecticut [Storrs] campus, and the transfers of ownership of the lands dating back to the mid-eighteenth century up to and including the mid-twentieth century. The collection does not include any information pertaining to his personal life. A significant portion of the survey work appears to have been conducted by Thomas B. Danielson>.
Arrangement
Series I: University of Connecticut Land Survey (1761-1958) Surveyors notes on University property lines and deed notes on lands bought and sold.
Series II: Field Notes (1911-1976) Moss and Danielson field notes on University land topography including water commission, sewer level surveys, river and land visibility studies, and survey notes on deeded lands.
Series III: Land Deeds, Leases, Maps and Surveys (1773-1976) Official deeds and unofficial deed notes on properties conveyed to and from the University and property owners, including surveys of properties deeded. Maps of properties bought and sold, town lines, and Connecticut Light and Power surveys of University substations.
Series IV: Visual materials (1920-1965) This portion of the collection has been inventoried but not processed. Includes films, plate negatives and photos of Forestry work done in the United States.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. Walter Wardell in March 1994.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Location of Copies or Alternate Formats
Digital reproductions of materials in this collection may also be found in the Archives & Special Collections digital repository.
Notes; Photocopies; Plats (maps); Correspondence; Maps (documents); Photographs; Land surveys; Lantern slides; Field notes; Deeds; Moving images; Leases; Moss, Alfred E.; Danielson, Thomas B.
- Series I: University of Connecticut Land Survey, 1761-1958
  - Barrows. Notes on land deeds and surveys, 1811-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3, Folder 1, Folder 2)
  - UConn-East of route 195 and North of Gurleyville. Notes on land deeds and surveys, 1761-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5, Folder 6, Folder 4)
  - UConn-Horsebarn Road to Dog Lane. Notes on land deeds and surveys, 1813-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - UConn-North Eagleville Road. Notes on land deeds and surveys, 1763-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9, Folder 10, Folder 11)
  - UConn-South Eagleville Road to Dog Lane to South Coventry. Notes on land deeds and surveys, 1830-1950 (Box 2, Folder 12, Folder 13, Folder 14, Folder 15)
- Series II: Field Notes, 1911-1976
  - Volume 1, Survey of College Lands. Divided into sections A, B, C, D and page numbers. A: West Orchard to South Eagleville Road p.1-10, 1925 February 14 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Volume 2, Survey of College lands and buildings. Data and drawings of Road frontage, duck pond and ground levels to wells and river, 1925 July - August (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Volume 3 Survey of College lands. Profile of proposed pipeline. Water pipe survey. Sewer level survey profile of Fenton river and Fenton pond. Levels of filter beds, 1926 December - 1927 July (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Volume 4 Water commission notes. Index to notes in back of field book, 1927 July - September (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Volume 5 Water commission field notes. Survey notes, calculations. Tower topography notes, 1927 October - December (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Volume 6 Levels of sewers, filter beds. Gurleyville Road purchase. Calculations with references to book number and page. Dates out of sequence, 1927 December - 1930 August (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Volume 7 Land grading levels and elevations, 1927-1929 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - unmarked volume. Sketches of part of state forest at Portland. Survey calculations. Description and measurement of land and trees, including blight and other damage, 1911-1918 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - unmarked volume. Visibility studies on different tracts of land. Including date, weather, time, crew. Survey notes and remarks on land, 1938 April - August (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Fenton river-daily diary. Time, air temperature, water temperature, location and other miscellaneous notes, 1935 July (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Survey of UConn land near sheep and chicken range, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Survey of Ostrofsky land, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Survey of UConn pond and surveyors personal notes, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Survey of orchard area and chicken house, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Survey of UConn lands near water wells B and C, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Survey of Storrs family land, deed notes included, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Survey of UConn land, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Survey of UConn land, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Survey of Horsebarn Hill Road to North Eagleville Road, includes electric pole markings, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Survey of Gurleyville Road/Fenton River area, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Survey of Ledgebrook land and rear of skating rink, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Property notes and calculations, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Survey of UConn land on Gurleyville Road, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Notes on all activities done in the field, by surveyor and assistant, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Survey of Fitts property, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Survey of E.O. Smith/University High School grounds, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Survey of Agronomy Road and Orchard Road, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Survey of Gilmore family land on Dog Lane, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Survey of Jacobsen, Porizek and new Post Office land, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Survey and property deed notes on town of Chaplin, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Surveyors personal notes on work activity in the field, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - UConn land-Survey and property notes, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Survey of Connecticut Theatrical Corp. land, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Survey notes for Hirschfield Brothers Const Co., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Dewey family land notes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Survey of Barrows in town of Mansfield, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Survey of Weeks Agency land and new Post Office land, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Worksheet on land on the west side of Route 195, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Survey drawings of Brown and Gurley family lands, undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Deed notes-Baker to Clark, Isaac Farewell to John Farewell, Samuel Thompson to Hannah, Gordon, Jesse and Elijah Thompson, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Drawings and calculations for lines of separation of properties belonging to Freeman and Storrs families, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Series III: Land Deeds, Maps and Surveys, 1773-1976
  - Land deed Beach, Kirkpatrick and Wheeler to the State of Connecticut. (Mrs. M.B. Whitney 1914), 1917 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Land deed Joseph P. Brown (H. Day 1940), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Land deed Florence S. Cummings to Connecticut Agricultural College (Bradley M. Sears 1917), 1920 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Land deed John N. Fitts to State of Connecticut (Chadwick 1909, Mason 1916), 1918 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Land deed Freeman and Thompson families, 1788-1844 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Land deed Harold C. Hawkins to State of Connecticut (Gurleyville-west side of Fenton river, both sides of the highway), 1918 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Land deed Lydia E. Harris to Connecticut Agricultural College (village of Eagleville, eastward from Central Vermont passenger station), 1918 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Land deed Julius A. Hauschild (Eastside of Storrs through Springhill to Willimantic), 1928 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Land deed George G. Jacobsen to UConn, Willimantic Savings and Loan and Alexander Jarvis, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Land deed George G. Jacobsen 1st tract-East side of C.A.C. to Mansfield Four Corners, 50 acres. 2nd tract-Southside of Gurleyville Road, 54.4 acres, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Land deed Charles and Katie Muller to Connecticut Agricultural College (3 tracts in Mansfield, easterly of the Congregational Church in Storrs), 1918 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Land deed Charles T. and A. Lena Nichols to State of Connecticut (near village of Gurleyville- 5 acres) (Charles W. To Charles T. 1909), 1915 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Land deed Augustus Storrs to Trustees of the Storrs Agricultural School (A. Storrs establishes the state Agricultural School in 1881), 1890 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Land deed Storrs Congregational Church to State of Connecticut (easterly side of highway from Springhill to Storrs), 1929 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Land deed University Commercials, Inc. to State of Connecticut (State of CT to University Commercials, Inc. 1948), 1968 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Land deed Benjamin E. Valentine to State of Connecticut (tract starting in Mansfield to Storrs to Springhill to Willimantic), 1918 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Land deed Philomena A. and Esther W. Warzocha to State of Connecticut with right of way to Willimantic Trust Co. on Dog Lane, 1962, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Land deed State of Connecticut to Willimantic Trust Co. (southerly side of Dog Lane in town of Mansfield), 1962 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Land deed Willis P. and Olive G. Wildes to State of Connecticut and C.A.C. (Easterly side of the highway from Springhill to Storrs, 22 acres), 1928 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Land deed Monroe D. andPhyllis M. Wright to State of Connecticut and UConn (2.22 acres in Mansfield), 1958 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Land use, paced by AEM, 1923 (Item Conservation)
  - Agronomy Rd survey notes and deed notes, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Beebe family land deeds notes and survey notes, 1942-1969 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Board of Fisheries and Game notes, State of CT (tracts 180, 182), undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Survey of Daniel A. Graf land (east side of Moulton Rd), 1966 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Joseph Ogushewitz to State of Connecticut (farm south of Old Turnpike Rd), 1966 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Sophia Soja to State of Connecticut (tract known as Ox-Bow), 1959 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Stanley L. Storrs toState of Connecticut and UConn, survey and deed notes, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Albert E. Waugh notes on land deeded to and from UConn, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Weeks Agency to State of Connecticut (Allen King to Ellsworth Weeks, 1956 and Ellsworth Weeks to Weeks Agency, 1968), 1976 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Survey notes on Land on easterly side of UConn campus and route 195, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - State of Connecticut to University of Connecticut Foundation (westerly side of Hillside Rd), 1967 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - University of Connecticut to Willimantic Trust Co. (southerly side of Dog Lane in Mansfield), 1962 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - University of Connecticut to Hirschfield, survey and deed notes (Route 195 and Dog Lane), 1969 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - University of Connecticut to Stanley Werner Management Corp., Survey and deed notes (easterly side of route 195 in Mansfield), 1962 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - University of Connecticut to Warzocha and Willimantic Trust Co. (southerly side of Dog Lane in Mansfield), 1962 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Lease notes, State of Connecticut to U.S. Postal Service, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Lease notes, University of Connecticut to Uni-Plaza, Inc., 1972 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Property notes. Name of property owner, date, and MLR area, undated (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - C.A.C. Real Estate owned and from whom acquired, drawn by Moss and updated by Danielson (1967), 1881-1930 (Box OS:94)
  - Survey drawings pertaining to Weeks Agency, Inc. lands owned and sold, undated (Box OS:94)
  - Drawing of driveways off of Dog Lane leading to Bank and doctors office, undated (Box OS:94)
  - Survey drawings of properties along Beebe Lane and Route 195, circa 1950 (Box OS:94)
  - Location of right of way of The Connecticut Light and Power company, across property located in town of Mansfield, 1955 June (Box OS:94)
  - Three drawings of H.D. stranded conductors on UConn property next to Henry S. Day property line, undated (Box OS:94)
  - Map of land to be conveyed by Everest T. McKinney to State of Connecticut, Westerly of Conn Highway Route 195, town of Mansfield, 1952 February (Box OS:95)
  - Map of land to be conveyed by Isidore Rosenstein to Farhang Javid and Kathleen B. Javid, Northeasterly corner of North and Bolivia streets, Willimantic, CT, 1962 June (Box OS:96)
  - Maps of property conveyed by University Commercials, Inc. to State of Connecticut by deed dated September 1968. Survey October 1968, 2 maps (Box OS:97)
  - Plan showing proposed line and sub station site at UConn, 22KV line to UConn from Connecticut Light and Power Co. May 1948. Light and Power Co. survey map of the Rockville-Willimantic line stations and poles (Box OS:98)
  - UConn plant maintenance dept. maps, 1962 June (Box OS:99)
  - Map of Woodstock, CT, 1886 (Box OS:100)
  - Four sections of a map showing areas around Storrs University Plaza, undated (Box OS:100)
  - Plan of north half of the township of Woodstock, 1773 May (Box OS:100)
  - Connecticut State Highway dept. right of way map of town of Mansfield, Willimantic-Storrs Road, 1933 (Box OS:100)
- Series IV: Personal Papers, undated, 1938, 1959-1978
  - Thomas B. Danielson, 1959-1978 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Alfred E. Moss, undated, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 93)
- Series V: Visual Materials, undated, 1920-1965
  Access
  Original photographic negatives are not available for use due to their fragility. Original photographic prints in Series V, subseries C were made from the negatives.
  - Subseries A: Film, 1929-1962; 9 film reels; 16 mm.
    Originals not available due to fragility. Use reference copies.
    - Swamp logging, Longleaf Pine, Southern United States, 1936; 1 film reel (9 min., 37 sec.): si., col.; 16 mm. (Reel 1990-0031/MP1 P, Disk 1990-0031/DVD1 R, Cassette 1990-0031/VR1 I)
      Scope and Content Note
      Film depicts the logging of virgin forests of Longleaf Pines throughout the Southeast United States. The exact site is most likely North Carolina or Florida. The Longleaf Pine was valued for lumber and for its resin, which was used in navy stores, and the production of turpentine and rosin. By the time of this film the Longleaf Pine had been almost entirely cleared from North America and replaced with faster growing varieties of pine. The footage includes examples of the use of a steam donkey, or steam driven winch, a geared steam locamotive, a steam skidder, and a variety of hand tools. At 7 min. 33. a man is seen stripping bark off of pines to harvest resin. The camera focuses on two different views of his bark stripping tool. Researchers interested in this video will find slides from the same trip in Subseries B: Lantern Slides of the Alfred E. Moss Collection. Moss screened the film at a meeting of the Storrs Movie Makers Club. More on the club can be found in the Jerauld A. Manter Collection (MSS1991.0032). Total run time 9 min. 40 sec.
    - Forestry, Connecticut hardwood, logging, sawmill, circa 1929; 1 film reel (9 min., 12 sec.): si., b&w; 16 mm. (Disk 1990-0031/DVD1 R)
      Film depicts hardwood logging in Connecticut. Several students can be seen in the beginning of the footage measuring tree sizes and taking notes. Trees can be seen being loaded on to a horse-drawn sled. At 12 min. 20 sec. and 13 min. 55 sec. a sawmill is documented. At 18 min. the video cuts to the transplanting of seedlings in a garden plot. Total run time 10 min. 23 sec.
    - Logging, Maine, circa 1951; 1 film reel (18 min., 31 sec.): si., b&w and col.; 16 mm. (Cassette 1990-0031/VR1 I, Reel 1990-0031/MP3 P, Disk 1990-0031/DVD1 R)
      University of Connecticut students in the former town of Davidson, Maine at the location of the Summit Lumber Company. Film documents students involved in surveying, logging, recreation activities and life in camp. Total run time 18 min. 28 sec.
    - Chopping contest, circa 1932; 1 film reel (4 min.): si., b&w; 16 mm. (Reel 1990-0031/MP4 P, Disk 1990-0031/DVD1 R)
      Film documents a wood chopping contest hosted by the Hartford Farm Bureau. The winner recieves a cash prize and runner up participants are awarded new axe heads. Total run time 3 min. 3 sec.
    - Chopping contest, Connecticut Agricultural College, circa 1932; 1 film reel (3 min., 31 sec); si., b&w; 16 mm. (Cassette 1990-0031/VR1 I, Disk 1990-0031/DVD1 R, Reel 1990-0031/MP5 P)
      Film documents a controlled burn demonstration and then cuts to a wood chopping competition in front of the Hawley Armory Building at the Connecticut Agricultural College. Film was likely taken the same day as MSS1990.0031/MP4. Film ends with several seconds of men chopping trees in a river. Total run time 3 min. 8 sec.
    - Felling Trees with jack, circa 1956; 1 film reel (7 min., 2 sec.): si., col.; 16 mm. (Reel 1990-0031/MP6 P, Cassette 1990-0031/VR2 I, Disk 1990-0031/DVD2 R)
      Film documents a method for felling trees. A direction cut is made and then a portion of the felling cut. The demonstrator then cuts a notch into the opposite side of the directional cut, inserts a jack and fells the tree using the jack. Film may have been made for classroom or Extension Service work. Total run time 7 min. 5 sec.
    - Water wheel detail, circa 1936; 1 film reel (1 min., 42 sec.): si., b&w; 16 mm. (Cassette 1990-0031/VR2 I, Disk 1990-0031/DVD2 R, Reel 1990-0031/MP7 P)
      Close up of a water wheel. Moss was a member of the Storrs Movie Makers Club and the film may have been shot for that. More on the club can be found in the Jerauld A. Manter Collection (MSS1991.0032)Total run time 1 min. 34 sec.
    - Tree Planting Instructional, circa 1962; 1 film reel (10 min., 2 sec.): si., b&w: 16 mm. (Disk 1990-0031/DVD2 R, Reel 1990-0031/MP8 P, Cassette 1990-0031/VR2 I)
      Film provides instructions for the planting of conifer seedlings. Two steps are covered, planting seedlings as bunch to allow them to root, and then seperating and planting individual seedlings. Camera pans over tools needed at start. Total run time 10 min. 30 sec.
    - Org Fallout Films, SOF Fallout in Food, circa 1962; 1 film reel (25 min., 7 sec.): sd., b&w; 16 mm. (Cassette 1990-0031/VR2 I, Disk 1990-0031/DVD2 R, Reel 1990-0031/MP9 P)
      Fallout in Food was produced for This Is UConn by the College of Agriculture. Film was directed at housewives and interviews University faculty and experts in the field about the risks of nucear fallout, particularly that of Strontium 90, contamination in meat, milk, prepackaged and canned foods, fruits, and vegetables. UConn faculty include; Donald Kinsman of the Department of Animal Husbandry, Joe McNeil, a food scientist, and Fred Ellers of the Department of Plant Sciences. Emphasis is on the relative safety of milk products and how to de-contanimate food in the event of nuclear fallout, or radioactive dust. Film mentions government testing facilities in Oakridge, TN. The program "This is UConn" was shown on Channel 8, Connecticut Public Television. More on radiation testing at UConn can be found in the University of Connecticut, President's Office Records, Homer D. Babbidge Collection (MSS1998.0183) and more on the College of Agriculture's response to public fears about nuclear fallout can be found in the College of Agriculture collection (MSS1997.0010). Total run time 25 min. 15 sec.
  - Subseries B: Lantern slides, 1928-1933
    - Forestry activities and 4-H, New England, 1928-1933; 49 lantern slides, b&w, hand col. (Box 7, Box 6)
      Includes trips to Cathedral Pines, Cornwall; White Plantation, Eagleville; Shaker Pines, Enfield; Cushman Farm, North Grandby; R. & W. Pine Plantation, Maine; Goodwin Forest; Shaker Pines, Hazardville; 4-H forestry activities documented include trail construction, C.S.C. trails, fire and cattle damage to forests, Christmas tree planting, planting and timber estimating. Original container for lantern slides labeled "Extension Service, Storrs, Connecticut."
    - Connecticut Agricultural College logging activities, circa 1912; 47 lantern slides, b&w (Box 13)
      Lantern slides manufactured by W.C. Ives, Mystic, Connecticut.
    - Logging activities, 1910-911; 37 lantern slides, b&w, hand col. (Box 8)
      Includes documentation of lumber companies, cutting, saw mills, log drives, some on the Columbia River, Oregon.
    - Forestry activities, Hawaii, New Mexico, California, Florida, Europe, circa 1901; 44 lantern slides, b&w, hand col. (Box 7)
      Lantern slide manufacturers represented include T. H. McAllister Manufacturing Optician, Detroit Photographic Company, Maison de la Bonne Presse.
    - Colorado, Wyoming and Rocky Mountain National Park, 1923; 40 lantern slides, b&w, hand col. (Box 9)
    - U.S. Forest Service forestry activities, Colorado, Wyoming, Washington, California, Alaska, Oregon, North Carolina, Virginia, circa 1914; 39 lantern slides, b&w, hand col. (Box 10)
    - Western forests, Oregon, Utah, California, Yellowstone National Park, Yosemite National Park, undated; 45 lantern slides, b&w, hand col. (Box 12, Box 11)
      Lantern slides manufactured by Art Photo Co., Springfield and New Haven; Haynes Stuidos, St. Paul, Minnesota; J. Levy & Cie, Paris.
    - Forestry activities, Gulf Coast Highway, North Carolina, Alabama, Florida, 1936; 38 lantern slides, b&w (Box 12)
  - Subseries C: Photographic prints, 1920-1965
    - Trout opening day, Willimantic River, 1935 May 1 (Box 14)
      Photographs document stocking of the Willimantic River with brown trout.
    - Fenton River stream improvement, 1933-1935 (Box 14)
      Photographs document stream improvement activities, including trout planting, artificial debris placement, barrier creation.
    - Roaring Brook, 1934-1935 (Box 14)
    - Natchaug River, 1934-1935 (Box 14)
      Photographs document stream improvements one year after implementation.
    - Stream improvements, 1934-1935 (Box 14)
      Photographs document stream improvements in Mt. Hope River, Farmington River and Daleville.
    - Forestry and logging, Northeastern Connecticut, 1933-1962; 30 photographic prints, b&w (Box 14)
      Includes forestry camp in Union, Connecticut; fire plots in Gurleyville; forests in Mansfield Depot; thinning of the Pine Acres Farm, Hampton, Connecticut.